Catholic Studies Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Catholic Studies Collection
1870 – 2003
NPkMC-222-215
7.5 Linear Feet
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Louis Zuccarello (Marist Heritage Professor)
The Catholic Studies Collection consists of both local materials pertaining to the state of New York and Dutchess County, as well as general materials on Catholicism throughout the United States and abroad. The collection contains parish histories, the papers and preparation notes of Louis Zuccarello, videos, photographs of local churches, audio tapes, materials on education, essays, and various newspapers and newspaper clippings on issues pertaining to Catholicism.
Collection Overview
The Catholic Studies Collection contains various documents, photographs, books, essays, pamphlets, newspapers, and audio and video tapes all having to do with Catholicism and/ or topics which touched on Catholicism and the lives of Catholics in the years from 1870 through 2003.
Acquisitions Informantion
The Catholic Studies Collection was given to the Marist Library by Louis Zuccarello.
Biographical Note
Catholicism has played an important role in Dutchess County as Louis Zuccarello set out to show by compiling this collection. With parishes springing up all over Dutchess County to serve the needs of the various ethnic groups, Catholicism was a vital element of the community and in America in general. American bishops in New York and the Dutchess area, like Nilan and Burtsell were getting involved in trying to reform the religion and align it more closely with people’s lifestyles and values in America, as the Americanism school of thought sprung up and climaxed in the late 1800s. Catholicism also played an important role in the education of the local populace as different parishes opened up their own schools, colleges, and seminaries.
Restrictions to Access
There are no restrictions on this collection
Materials are arranged into two series: 1) Catholic Studies, general, with seven subseries, and 2) The Catholic Church in New York, with seven subseries.
- 1. Catholic Studies, general, 1; Boxes: 1 - 2 Folders: 1 - 63
  Series contains subseries Newspapers, Books/ Journals on Law, History, and Catholicism, Audio Visual Materials, Education, College, Sodality, Assorted, General
  Subject
  - Subseries 1.1: Newspapers, 1.1; Box: 1 Folders: 1 - 5
    Series contains a collection of assorted Catholic New York Newspapers spanning from 1983 – 2000. There is also an issue of Stars and Stripes covering Desert Storm and Queen of Peace from 1995.
    Chronological
    - Catholic New York. (Folder 1, Box 1)
    - Catholic New York. (Folder 2, Box 1)
    - Catholic New York. (Folder 3, Box 1)
    - Stars and Stripes. (Folder 4, Box 1)
    - Queen of Peace. (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - Subseries 1.2: Books/ Journals on Law, History, and Catholicism, 1.2; Box: 1 Folders: 6 - 12
    Series contains various books and journals dealing with different Catholic issues and history.
    - Past and Present. A Journal of History and Government. Vol. II (1957). St. John’s University. (Folder 6, Box 1)
    - Carthy, Mother Mary Peter. “English Influences on Early American Catholicism.” Vol. XLIV (1959). Washington, D.C.: The Catholic University of America Press. (Folder 7, Box 1)
    - The Catholic Lawyer. Vol. 9, No. 1 (1963). (Folder 8, Box 1)
    - Land and Water Law Review. “Conscription and the Conscientious Objectors”. Joseph F. Costanzo. Vol. VI, No. 2 (1971). (Folder 9, Box 1)
    - American Views on Religion, Politics and Public Policy. April 2001. The Pew Forum. (Folder 10, Box 1)
    - The Catholic Historical Review. Vol. LXXXIX, No. 2. April 2003. The Catholic Historical Review. Vol. LXXXIX, No. 3. July 2003. (Folder 11, Box 1)
    - U.S. Catholic Historian. Vol. 21. No. 3. Summer 2003. (Folder 12, Box 1)
  - Subseries 1.3: Audio Visual Materials, 1.3; Box: 1 Folders: 13 - 17
    Series contains video tapes and audio cassettes covering the Focolare Movement, Marist College, and other topics in Catholicism.
    Size
    - Knowledge Mgt. Focus Group. Marist Retirees discuss Marist teaching approaches. April 3, 2002. Senior Faculty. May 14, 2002. (Folder 13, Box 1)
    - Cassette Tapes. Radio Free Europe. Radio Liberty. Mar. 14, 1986. Trinity Urban Issues Forum. Oct. 11, 1995. (Folder 14, Box 1)
    - Bishop Fulton J. Sheen. “Life is Worth Living.” 1992. (Focolare Movement) (Folder 15, Box 1)
    - DeMello, Anthony S.J. Sadhana: A Way to God. Christian Exercises in Eastern Form. (Folder 16, Box 1)
    - Lubich, Chiara. “What We Are.” April 2002. (Focolare Movement) (Folder 17, Box 1)
  - Subseries 1.4: Education, 1.4; Box: 2 Folders: 18 - 32
    Series contains assorted documents, posters, pamphlets, and newsletters dealing with education.
    - Ad Campaign for better Schools, 1943, 1949-1951. (Folder 18, Box 2)
    - American Council on Education. (Folder 19, Box 2)
    - American Education Week. (Folder 20, Box 2)
    - Bulletins for institutions of Higher Learning.1944-1952. (Folder 21, Box 2)
    - Committee of the Catholic Commission on Intellectual and Cultural Affairs (Folder 22, Box 2)
    - Curriculum Conference for Catholic Schools (Folder 23, Box 2)
    - Federal Aid to Education (Folder 24, Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Newsletters (Folder 25, Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Pamphlets on Education (Folder 26, Box 2)
    - National Catholic Education Association (Folder 27, Box 2)
    - NCEA Convention. (Folder 28, Box 2)
    - Notes and Comment on General Education. 1950 - 1952. (Folder 29, Box 2)
    - Radio and Education (Folder 30, Box 2)
    - Religious Book Week (Folder 31, Box 2)
    - Senate Legislation (Folder 32, Box 2)
  - Subseries 1.5: College, 1.5; Box: 2 Folders: 33 - 41
    Series contains various documents dealing with higher education. There are materials from the Catholic University of America as well as studies and other information on college.
    - The Catholic University of America. (Folder 33, Box 2)
    - The Catholic University of America. The Workshop on College Organization and Administration. 1. (Folder 34, Box 2)
    - The Catholic University of America. The Workshop on College Organization and Administration. 2. (Folder 35, Box 2)
    - College and Church. (Folder 36, Box 2)
    - College Graduates in Industry. (Folder 37, Box 2)
    - Fordham (Folder 38, Box 2)
    - Higher Education (Folder 39, Box 2)
    - National Commission on Christian Higher Education (Folder 40, Box 2)
    - The State Education Dept. (Folder 41, Box 2)
  - Subseries 1.6: Sodality, 1.6; Box: 2 Folders: 42 - 44
    Series contains various materials having to do with sodality, including the Parish Red Book for Sodality, Instructions for Sodality Candidates, and pamphlets.
    Alphabetical
    - Instruction of Sodality Candidates. (Folder 42, Box 2)
    - Parish Sodalist’s Red Book. (Folder 43, Box 2)
    - Sodality Pamphlets - The Queen’s Work (Folder 44, Box 2)
  - Subseries 1.7: Assorted, General, 1.7; Box: 2 Folders: 45 - 63
    Series contains documents spanning a host of topics dealing with Catholicism and the World War years, mostly from the early – middle 1900s.
    - The Antigonish Way (Folder 45, Box 2)
    - Between the Lines (Folder 46, Box 2)
    - Child Labor (Folder 47, Box 2)
    - Christian Social Living (Folder 48, Box 2)
    - Christmas (Folder 49, Box 2)
    - The Christophers (Folder 50, Box 2)
    - The Ford Foundation (Folder 51, Box 2)
    - Forest Industry Pamphlets (Folder 52, Box 2)
    - Foreign Affairs Outline: Building the Peace. (Folder 53, Box 2)
    - For Women Only. Newspaper Section. (Folder 54, Box 2)
    - French Religious Newsletter. Issues 1- 6. (Folder 55, Box 2)
    - French Religious Newsletter Issues 7 - 12. (Folder 56, Box 2)
    - International Religious Publications (Folder 57, Box 2)
    - Mary’s Garden (Folder 58, Box 2)
    - National Catholic Welfare Conference (Folder 59, Box 2)
    - Our Lady (Folder 60, Box 2)
    - Ten Outstanding Magazine Articles. 1946 - 1949. (Folder 61, Box 2)
    - Vocations (Folder 62, Box 2)
    - Writings on Spirituality (Folder 63, Box 2)
- 2. The Catholic Church in New York, 2; Boxes: 3 - 5 Folders: 64 - 133
  Series contains the subseries References, bibliography, Notes for Zuccarello’s Papers on the Church, Ethnic Issues, Dutchess County History, Churches/ Parishes in New York, Marist College, and Miscellaneous
  - Subseries 2.1: References, bibliography, 2.1; Box: 3 Folders: 64 - 66
    Series contains references and bibliographies complied by Louis Zuccarello while doing research for his papers on Catholics in the Dutchess area.
    Original Order (Approximately)
    - Selected bibliographies and references. (Folder 64, Box 3)
    - Catholic Scholars (Folder 65, Box 3)
    - Citations from Poughkeepsie Journal and Daily Eagle (Folder 66, Box 3)
  - Subseries 2.2: Notes for Zuccarello’s Papers on the Church, 2.2; Box: 3 Folders: 67 - 73
    Series contains notes taken while researching Catholicism in Dutchess County along with drafts of papers on the topic and correspondence relating to the research process.
    - Background Information for Papers (Folder 67, Box 3)
    - Correspondence relating to research on Catholics in the Mid-Hudson Area (Folder 68, Box 3)
    - Correspondence, Copies of Notes. (Folder 69, Box 3)
    - Notes on Papers, Catholics in Poughkeepsie (Folder 70, Box 3)
    - Drafts. The Catholic Community in Poughkeepsie, 1870 - 1900: The Period of Testing (Folder 71, Box 3)
    - The Catholic Community in Poughkeepsie, 1870 - 1900: The Period of Testing. Editing of the Original. (Folder 72, Box 3)
    - Transformation of an American County. Tercentary Conference. Pluralism in the Catholic Community in 19th Century Poughkeepsie. (Folder 73, Box 3)
  - Subseries 2.3: Ethnic Issues, 2.3; Box: 3 Folders: 74 - 78
    Series contains various documents and newspapers clippings pertaining to ethnic groups in New York and their interaction with one another.
    - Ethnics in Poughkeepsie and Dutchess (Folder 74, Box 3)
    - Ethnics - Black Catholics (Folder 75, Box 3)
    - Italian American Experience in U.S. and Poughkeepsie. Materials and Clippings. (Folder 76, Box 3)
    - Ethnic Politics Materials (Folder 77, Box 3)
    - Smith, Alfred E. and Taft, Robert. Writings on, by Louis (Folder 78, Box 3)
  - Subseries 2.4: Dutchess County History, 2.4; Box: 3 Folders: 79 - 86
    Series contains includes a book of Louis Zuccarello’s papers on Catholicism in the Poughkeepsie area as well as Dutchess County, and Churches general history, as well as Poughkeepsie’s general history. There are also various newspaper clippings describing events in Dutchess County.
    - The Catholic Community in the Poughkeepsie Area, Louis Zuccarello. (Folder 79, Box 3)
    - Dutchess, general history. (Folder 80, Box 3)
    - Dutchess County, Church. (Folder 81, Box 3)
    - Dutchess Churches and Cemeteries. Photos and Clippings. (Folder 82, Box 3)
    - Dutchess Catholic Churches. (Folder 83, Box 3)
    - Catholic Church in Dutchess County. 1808 - 1983. (Folder 84, Box 3)
    - Poughkeepsie, NY, History. (Folder 85, Box 3)
    - Assorted Clippings (Folder 86, Box 3)
  - Subseries 2.5: Churches/ Parishes in New York, 2.5; Box: 4 Folders: 87 - 108
    Series contains documents, photographs, newspaper clippings, and census data detailing the history of various parishes in New York.
    - Archdiocese of New York Materials. (Folder 87, Box 4)
    - Parish Histories (Folder 88, Box 4)
    - Holy Trinity (Folder 89, Box 4)
    - Immaculate Conception (Folder 90, Box 4)
    - Mt. Carmel Parish. (Folder 91, Box 4)
    - Stations of the Cross. Mt. Carmel. (Folder 92, Box 4)
    - Mt. Carmel Parish Council Materials 1999 - 2000. 1 (Folder 93, Box 4)
    - Mt. Carmel Parish Council Materials 1999 - 2000. 2 (Folder 94, Box 4)
    - Mt. Carmel Parish Census, 2000 (Folder 95, Box 4)
    - Mt. Carmel Parish Council Materials, 2000 - 2001 (Folder 96, Box 4)
    - Nativity Church (Folder 97, Box 4)
    - Nativity Church, Translation of Anniversary Book (Folder 98, Box 4)
    - Regina Coeli (Folder 99, Box 4)
    - Sacred Heart Parish (Folder 100, Box 4)
    - St. John the Baptist (Folder 101, Box 4)
    - St. Joseph’s (Folder 102, Box 4)
    - St. Joseph’s Church (Folder 103, Box 4)
    - St. Martin de Porres (Folder 104, Box 4)
    - St. Mary’s (Folder 105, Box 4)
    - St. Peter’s Parish (Folder 106, Box 4)
    - St. Peter’s Cemetery and Celtic Cross War Memorial. Photographs Enclosed. ` (Folder 107, Box 4)
    - St. Peter’s Church (Folder 108, Box 4)
  - Subseries 2.6: Marist College, 2.6; Box: 5 Folders: 109 - 112
    Series contains various documents pertaining to Marist College’s history and the Marist Brothers who began the school. Includes newspaper clippings, faculty lists, and general documents.
    - Marist College New Faculty. (Folder 109, Box 5)
    - Marist College. Assorted Material (Folder 110, Box 5)
    - Tom Cornell Lecture at Marist (Folder 111, Box 5)
    - Marist College, St. Andrews History (Folder 112, Box 5)
  - Subseries 2.7: Miscellaneous, 2.7; Box: 5 Folders: 113 - 133
    Series contains other documents relating to Zuccarello’s research including documents, newspaper clippings and notes on leaders in the community, clubs, and prominent religious figures. There are also church bulletins, obituaries, and other documents on Catholic issues in the area.
    - Americanism, Articles (Folder 113, Box 5)
    - American Catholic Studies Newsletter. (Folder 114, Box 5)
    - Burtsell, McGlynn et al Accademia, North America (Folder 115, Box 5)
    - Catholic Charity (Folder 116, Box 5)
    - Catholic Studies Programs (Folder 117, Box 5)
    - Catholic & Philosophical Issues. (Folder 118, Box 5)
    - Catholic Women (Folder 119, Box 5)
    - Church Bulletins and Groups (Folder 120, Box 5)
    - Clippings and Articles on Catholic Issues (Folder 121, Box 5)
    - Clubs (Folder 122, Box 5)
    - Humanae Vitae (Folder 123, Box 5)
    - Leaders in the Community, Poughkeepsie (Folder 124, Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Religious Periodicals. (Folder 125, Box 5)
    - Nilan, James. 1 (Folder 126, Box 5)
    - Nilan, James. 2 (Folder 127, Box 5)
    - Obituaries (Folder 128, Box 5)
    - Papacy, Papacy Delegate Archbishop Satolli (Folder 129, Box 5)
    - Religion and the State Articles (Folder 130, Box 5)
    - Spellman, Francis Cardinal and Dunwoodie (Folder 131, Box 5)
    - St. Francis Hospital (Folder 132, Box 5)
    - Vassar (Folder 133, Box 5)